“My Dear Mr Pip:-
“I write this by request of Mr. Gargery, for to let you know that he is going to London in
company with Mr. Wopsle and would be glad if agreeable to be allowed to see you. He would
call at Barnard’s Hotel Tuesday morning at nine o’clock, when if not agreeable please leave word.
Your poor sister is much the same as when you left. We talk of you in the kitchen every night,
and wonder what you are saying and doing. If now considered in the light of a liberty,
excuse it for the love of poor old days. No more, dear Mr. Pip, from
“Your ever obliged, and affectionate servant, “Biddy.”
“P.S. He wishes me most particular to write what larks. He says you will understand. I hope and
do not doubt it will be agreeable to see him, even though a gentleman, for you had ever a good heart,
and he is a worthy, worthy man. I have read him all, excepting only the last
little sentence, and he wishes me most particular to write again what larks.”
I received this letter by the post on Monday morning, and therefore its appointment was for
next day. Let me confess exactly with what feelings I looked forward to Joe’s coming.
Not with pleasure, though I was bound to him by so many ties; no; with considerable disturbance, some
mortification, and a keen sense of incongruity. If I could have kept him away by paying money,
I certainly would have paid money. My greatest reassurance was that he was
coming to Barnard’s Inn, not to Hammersmith, and consequently would not fall in Bentley
Drummle’s way. I had little objection to his being seen by Herbert or his father,
for both of whom I had a respect; but I had the sharpest sensitiveness as to his
being seen by Drummle, whom I held in contempt. So, throughout life, our worst weaknesses and
meannesses are usually committed for the sake of the people whom we most despise.
I had begun to be always decorating the chambers in some quite unnecessary and inappropriate way
or other, and very expensive those wrestles with Barnard proved to be. By this time,
the rooms were vastly different from what I had found them, and I enjoyed the honour of
occupying a few prominent pages in the books of a neighbouring upholsterer. I had got on
so fast of late, that I had even started a boy in boots,—top boots,—in bondage and slavery to whom
I might have been said to pass my days. For, after I had made the monster (out of the refuse
of my washerwoman’s family), and had clothed him with a blue coat, canary waistcoat, white cravat,
creamy breeches, and the boots already mentioned, I had to find him a little to do and a great deal
to eat; and with both of those horrible requirements he haunted my existence.
This avenging phantom was ordered to be on duty at eight on Tuesday morning in the hall,
(it was two feet square, as charged for floorcloth,) and Herbert suggested certain
things for breakfast that he thought Joe would like. While I felt sincerely obliged to him for
being so interested and considerate, I had an odd half-provoked sense of suspicion upon me,
that if Joe had been coming to see him, he wouldn’t have been quite so brisk about it.
However, I came into town on the Monday night to be ready for Joe, and I got up early in
the morning, and caused the sitting-room and breakfast-table to assume their most splendid
appearance. Unfortunately the morning was drizzly, and an angel could not have concealed the fact
that Barnard was shedding sooty tears outside the window, like some weak giant of a Sweep.
As the time approached I should have liked to run away, but the Avenger pursuant to orders
was in the hall, and presently I heard Joe on the staircase. I knew it was Joe, by his
clumsy manner of coming upstairs,—his state boots being always too big for him,—and by the time it
took him to read the names on the other floors in the course of his ascent. When at last he stopped
outside our door, I could hear his finger tracing over the painted letters of my name,
and I afterwards distinctly heard him breathing in at the keyhole. Finally he gave a faint single
rap, and Pepper—such was the compromising name of the avenging boy—announced “Mr. Gargery!”
I thought he never would have done wiping his feet,
and that I must have gone out to lift him off the mat, but at last he came in.
“Joe, how are you, Joe?”
“Pip, how AIR you, Pip?”
With his good honest face all glowing and shining, and his hat put down on the floor between us, he
caught both my hands and worked them straight up and down, as if I had been the last-patented Pump.
“I am glad to see you, Joe. Give me your hat.”
But Joe, taking it up carefully with both hands,
like a bird’s-nest with eggs in it, wouldn’t hear of parting with that piece of property,
and persisted in standing talking over it in a most uncomfortable way.
“Which you have that growed,” said Joe, “and that swelled, and that gentle-folked;” Joe considered a
little before he discovered this word; “as to be sure you are a honour to your king and country.”
“And you, Joe, look wonderfully well.” “Thank God,” said Joe,
“I’m ekerval to most. And your sister, she’s no worse than she were. And Biddy, she’s ever right
and ready. And all friends is no backerder, if not no forarder. ’Ceptin Wopsle; he’s had a drop.”
All this time (still with both hands taking great care of the bird’s-nest), Joe was rolling
his eyes round and round the room, and round and round the flowered pattern of my dressing-gown.
“Had a drop, Joe?”
“Why yes,” said Joe, lowering his voice, “he’s left the Church and went into the
playacting. Which the playacting have likeways brought him to London along with
me. And his wish were,” said Joe, getting the bird’s-nest under his left arm for the moment,
and groping in it for an egg with his right; “if no offence, as I would ’and you that.”
I took what Joe gave me, and found it to be the crumpled play-bill of a small metropolitan
theatre, announcing the first appearance, in that very week, of “the celebrated Provincial
Amateur of Roscian renown, whose unique performance in the highest tragic walk
of our National Bard has lately occasioned so great a sensation in local dramatic circles.”
“Were you at his performance, Joe?” I inquired.
“I were,” said Joe, with emphasis and solemnity.
“Was there a great sensation?”
“Why,” said Joe, “yes, there certainly were a peck of orange-peel. Partickler when he see the ghost.
Though I put it to yourself, sir, whether it were calc’lated to keep a man up to his work with a
good hart, to be continiwally cutting in betwixt him and the Ghost with “Amen!” A man may have had
a misfortun’ and been in the Church,” said Joe, lowering his voice to an argumentative and feeling
tone, “but that is no reason why you should put him out at such a time. Which I meantersay,
if the ghost of a man’s own father cannot be allowed to claim his attention, what can,
Sir? Still more, when his mourning ’at is unfortunately made so small as that
the weight of the black feathers brings it off, try to keep it on how you may.”
A ghost-seeing effect in Joe’s own countenance informed me that Herbert
had entered the room. So, I presented Joe to Herbert, who held out his hand;
but Joe backed from it, and held on by the bird’s-nest.
“Your servant, Sir,” said Joe, “which I hope as you and Pip”—here his eye fell on the Avenger,
who was putting some toast on table, and so plainly denoted an intention to make that young
gentleman one of the family, that I frowned it down and confused him more—“I meantersay,
you two gentlemen,—which I hope as you get your elths in this close spot? For
the present may be a werry good inn, according to London opinions,” said Joe, confidentially,
“and I believe its character do stand it; but I wouldn’t keep a pig in it myself,—not in the
case that I wished him to fatten wholesome and to eat with a meller flavour on him.”
Having borne this flattering testimony to the merits of our dwelling-place, and having
incidentally shown this tendency to call me “sir,” Joe, being invited to sit down to table,
looked all round the room for a suitable spot on which to deposit his hat,—as if it were only on
some very few rare substances in nature that it could find a resting place,—and ultimately stood
it on an extreme corner of the chimney-piece, from which it ever afterwards fell off at intervals.
“Do you take tea, or coffee, Mr. Gargery?” asked Herbert, who always presided of a morning.
“Thankee, Sir,” said Joe, stiff from head to foot,
“I’ll take whichever is most agreeable to yourself.”
“What do you say to coffee?”
“Thankee, Sir,” returned Joe, evidently dispirited by the proposal,
“since you are so kind as make chice of coffee,
I will not run contrairy to your own opinions. But don’t you never find it a little ’eating?”
“Say tea then,” said Herbert, pouring it out.
Here Joe’s hat tumbled off the mantel-piece, and he started out of his chair and picked it up,
and fitted it to the same exact spot. As if it were an absolute
point of good breeding that it should tumble off again soon.
“When did you come to town, Mr. Gargery?”
“Were it yesterday afternoon?” said Joe, after coughing behind his hand, as if he
had had time to catch the whooping-cough since he came. “No it were not. Yes it were. Yes. It
were yesterday afternoon” (with an appearance of mingled wisdom, relief, and strict impartiality).
“Have you seen anything of London yet?”
“Why, yes, Sir,” said Joe, “me and Wopsle went off straight to look at the Blacking Ware’us. But we
didn’t find that it come up to its likeness in the red bills at the shop doors; which I
meantersay,” added Joe, in an explanatory manner, “as it is there drawd too architectooralooral.”
I really believe Joe would have prolonged this word (mightily expressive to my mind
of some architecture that I know) into a perfect Chorus, but for his attention being providentially
attracted by his hat, which was toppling. Indeed, it demanded from him a constant attention, and a
quickness of eye and hand, very like that exacted by wicket-keeping. He made extraordinary play with
it, and showed the greatest skill; now, rushing at it and catching it neatly as it dropped; now,
merely stopping it midway, beating it up, and humouring it in various parts of the room and
against a good deal of the pattern of the paper on the wall, before he felt it safe to close with it;
finally splashing it into the slop-basin, where I took the liberty of laying hands upon it.
As to his shirt-collar, and his coat-collar, they were perplexing to reflect upon,—insoluble
mysteries both. Why should a man scrape himself to that extent, before he could consider himself full
dressed? Why should he suppose it necessary to be purified by suffering for his holiday clothes?
Then he fell into such unaccountable fits of meditation, with his fork midway between his
plate and his mouth; had his eyes attracted in such strange directions; was afflicted
with such remarkable coughs; sat so far from the table, and dropped so much more than he ate, and
pretended that he hadn’t dropped it; that I was heartily glad when Herbert left us for the City.
I had neither the good sense nor the good feeling to know that this was all my fault,
and that if I had been easier with Joe, Joe would have been easier with me. I felt impatient
of him and out of temper with him; in which condition he heaped coals of fire on my head.
“Us two being now alone, sir,”—began Joe.
“Joe,” I interrupted, pettishly, “how can you call me, sir?”
Joe looked at me for a single instant with something faintly
like reproach. Utterly preposterous as his cravat was, and as his collars were,
I was conscious of a sort of dignity in the look.
“Us two being now alone,” resumed Joe, “and me having the intentions and abilities to
stay not many minutes more, I will now conclude—leastways begin—to mention what
have led to my having had the present honour. For was it not,” said Joe,
with his old air of lucid exposition, “that my only wish were to be useful to you,
I should not have had the honour of breaking wittles in the company and abode of gentlemen.”
I was so unwilling to see the look again, that I made no remonstrance against this tone.
“Well, sir,” pursued Joe, “this is how it were. I were at the Bargemen t’other night,
Pip;”—whenever he subsided into affection,
he called me Pip, and whenever he relapsed into politeness he called me sir; “when there come up
in his shay-cart, Pumblechook. Which that same identical,” said Joe, going down a new track,
“do comb my ’air the wrong way sometimes, awful, by giving out up and down town as it were him
which ever had your infant companionation and were looked upon as a playfellow by yourself.”
“Nonsense. It was you, Joe.”
“Which I fully believed it were, Pip,” said Joe, slightly tossing his head, “though it signify
little now, sir. Well, Pip; this same identical, which his manners is given to blusterous, come
to me at the Bargemen (wot a pipe and a pint of beer do give refreshment to the workingman, sir,
and do not over stimilate), and his word were, ‘Joseph, Miss Havisham she wish to speak to you.’”
“Miss Havisham, Joe?”
“‘She wish,’ were Pumblechook’s word, ‘to speak to you.’” Joe sat and rolled his eyes at the ceiling.
“Yes, Joe? Go on, please.”
“Next day, sir,” said Joe, looking at me as if I were a long way off,
“having cleaned myself, I go and I see Miss A.”
“Miss A., Joe? Miss Havisham?”
“Which I say, sir,” replied Joe, with an air of legal formality,
as if he were making his will, “Miss A., or otherways Havisham. Her expression air
then as follering: ‘Mr. Gargery. You air in correspondence with Mr. Pip?’
Having had a letter from you, I were able to say ‘I am.’ (When I married your sister,
sir, I said ‘I will;’ and when I answered your friend, Pip, I said ‘I am.’) ‘Would you tell him,
then,’ said she, ‘that which Estella has come home and would be glad to see him.’”
I felt my face fire up as I looked at Joe. I hope one remote cause of its firing may have been my
consciousness that if I had known his errand, I should have given him more encouragement.
“Biddy,” pursued Joe, “when I got home and asked her fur to write the message to you,
a little hung back. Biddy says, ‘I know he will be very glad to have it by word of mouth, it is
holiday time, you want to see him, go!’ I have now concluded, sir,” said Joe, rising from his chair,
“and, Pip, I wish you ever well and ever prospering to a greater and a greater height.”
“But you are not going now, Joe?”
“Yes I am,” said Joe.
“But you are coming back to dinner, Joe?”
“No I am not,” said Joe.
Our eyes met, and all the “Sir” melted out of that manly heart as he gave me his hand.
“Pip, dear old chap, life is made of ever so many partings welded together, as I may say,
and one man’s a blacksmith, and one’s a whitesmith, and one’s a goldsmith, and one’s
a coppersmith. Diwisions among such must come, and must be met as they come. If there’s been
any fault at all to-day, it’s mine. You and me is not two figures to be together in London; nor yet
anywheres else but what is private, and beknown, and understood among friends. It ain’t that I am
proud, but that I want to be right, as you shall never see me no more in these clothes. I’m wrong
in these clothes. I’m wrong out of the forge, the kitchen, or off th’ meshes. You won’t find
half so much fault in me if you think of me in my forge dress, with my hammer in my hand, or even my
pipe. You won’t find half so much fault in me if, supposing as you should ever wish to see me, you
come and put your head in at the forge window and see Joe the blacksmith, there, at the old anvil,
in the old burnt apron, sticking to the old work. I’m awful dull, but I hope I’ve beat out something
nigh the rights of this at last. And so GOD bless you, dear old Pip, old chap, GOD bless you!”
I had not been mistaken in my fancy that there was a simple dignity in him. The fashion of his dress
could no more come in its way when he spoke these words than it could come in its way in Heaven. He
touched me gently on the forehead, and went out. As soon as I could recover myself sufficiently,
I hurried out after him and looked for him in the neighbouring streets;
but he was gone. Chapter 28.